[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
dan moore is ceo and co-founder of
vaporware a consultancy delivering
custom software to solve challenges or
disrupt industries
recently dan has also become co-founder
of the app awaiting
a virtual waitlist for brick and mortar
stores during the coven 19 pandemic
dan brings a decade of software
development experience and leadership as
a founder and engineer
dan thank you for coming on software
engineering radio today thanks for
having me adam
i'm really excited to talk about this
topic today on build versus buy because
it's actually
very close to home for me my day job i
work a lot with software as a director
and one of the
recent discussion i've had was around
build versus buy on software
we had to decide between some external
service that we wanted to use versus
building it ourselves
so i actually really want to start with
a scenario to frame this discussion
and then sort of ask you for advice on
how you would approach these things
so yeah i basically want to just dive
right in i'm not going to reveal any
sort of
details about the specific
implementation we had because that's not
really important what's important is
how you i think frame things and start
to create decisions around this
so you know the basic sort of context is
you need a tool that does x y and z and
in our particular case
we had already built x and y so a subset
of it and we found that there was
software that built
y and z so there was some overlapping
pieces but there were also pieces that
we had that the customer or the vendor
couldn't offer
and then the vendor had a lot of things
that we just didn't have time to build
so you know what i want to frame this
conversation is if you're a person out
there who is making this build versus by
decision how do you start to think about
choosing between these two options yeah
i think that there's
tons of factors and and a lot of it
comes
natural depending on what we've done in
the past as individuals
so my background i'm a software
developer by trade
a computer science graduate been
programming since
before i can remember and my natural
tendency has always been like
let's just start building that's that's
a problem i can solve it let's do it
over the past eight years with with our
consultancy
i've really had to go into this this
mode
what is the business need what's what's
the business trade-offs what are all
these different things that we have to
evaluate
so cost is definitely the first thing
that comes to mind just
what are we financially spending but
there's also a lot of
other types of costs and other types of
rewards that that we like to evaluate
in the work that we do so even once we
decide to build and solve a problem
there's tons of choices on
well do we buy or build every single
little piece
in between and there's some other
options in there too of
can we partner or can we acquire or
can we integrate in some way and all the
hybrid
options in between that once we get down
into the nitty-gritty
really start to become clear as we go
through those options so
for this one example that you're talking
about what's what's kind of that
that background or that that history of
of the team that got together to
to make these decisions yeah and i think
the important thing here is that
cost is a very blanket term right like
there's costs associated with
what is the sticker price of the vendor
software you're going to buy but there's
also the cost of
what would it take to implement
ourselves and i'm guessing what you're
talking about with history here is
do you know what the capabilities of
your development team are how much are
you paying them and what would it cost
in terms of you know people hours to
actually build this stuff over the next
n number of months so what kinds of
costs when you when you're breaking it
down how are you evaluating cost
so that's both in terms of full-time
employee equivalence it's in terms of
not just the initial build costs but the
initial discovery cost of
what exactly is it that needs to be
built there's hosting and longer term
support costs
but i think one one thing that's often
overlooked in terms of cost is also the
opportunity
cost of what else could this team be
doing so not just
what is the cost of this solution but
what is the cost of
the other solutions that they could be
building so
those are definitely some of the factors
that we consider for
actually dedicating a team or even just
a single person in a couple of hours
understanding what that value that
they're bringing and
creating is about right so when you talk
about opportunity costs you're really
talking about
are your developers or are the people on
your teams
building the most i guess ip defensible
works that they could possibly do right
because if it's commodity work with
commodity software why would you have
them reinvent the wheel and they can do
something that
is valuable to just your business right
exactly so what is that competitive
advantage that
you and your organization has and what
do you really need to be the experts on
compared to um you know are you just
reinventing
a small piece that someone else is
already the expert on that
can get you five times the distance and
half the time
to integrate it so there's there's
definitely
pieces there and let's say you know
you're really saving five hundred
dollars in sticker price
on having your team rebuild this
solution that's
that's already out there versus the five
thousand dollars that your organization
can be making in terms of profit
from them building and working on the
next feature
that no one else can do and are there
any hidden costs you consider as well
too because
i imagine it's not just as simple as
this vendor software costs x
and my developers cost x per hour
amortized over their salaries there must
be other sort of costs that you sort of
factor into in terms of you know besides
opportunity costs that might
you know change the dynamics of how you
evaluate this decision
absolutely so there's a lot of hidden
costs when
buying solutions off the shelf and we
see that in terms of
integration costs or cost to other sides
of the business so
if you're not building software that is
unique
and specifically tailored around your
business operations that you already
have set up
you're buying software off the shelf and
have to readjust
the business operations to match the
software
so sometimes that's a really good thing
when it's a general industry practice
gap accounting principles for example of
multiple accounts and being able to
recognize books and revenue the proper
way that makes sense for outside
auditors
that's a really good thing to push for
is industry standards but if it's unique
to your business
and like let's say you invoice on a
completely unique
schedule and type of payment process
then that may be something that you need
custom that you don't want to change
your business and change the ultimate
and business
opportunity for so it's
not always black and white in terms of
like we buy this thing and it just
magically works
it's okay now that we have it inside of
our organization and now that we have
access to it
how does the organization morph and
change around that
yeah that reminds me that the way we
kind of evaluated this was through a
spreadsheet we basically made this
massive spreadsheet
of all of the things we needed a kind of
software to do whether it was our own
or an external vendor or you know some
hybrid approach
and we just looked at all of them like i
said the vendor had x and y
or we had x and y and the vendor had y
and z and we just
enamored it through all of the options
and then basically looked at
you know which ones we had we had built
ourselves already which ones we were
planning on building and which ones we
knew we weren't going to be able to get
to any sort of reasonable future
and one thing that kind of came up that
helped us in our decision was
well okay let's say 50 of the things are
built by the vendor and 50
are built by us well what's the priority
of those things
so you know we looked at some of them
and we said well actually you know
these things we don't have but they're
also on the lower range of importance
for us the things that are really
important to us some of them might be
from the vendor but others might be
things we've already built because
through you know customer requests we
knew that those were really important to
tackle now
so priority and ranking definitely i
think is another one that was a big
decision for us in terms of how we're
going to evaluate a vendor
versus what we're going to build in
starting to think about a framework or a
checklist for me starting to make this
decision
what kinds of things do you put in a
spreadsheet do you even go to a
spreadsheet like how do you start
building out this kind of list of
evaluation criteria
yeah i think a spreadsheet is a great
asset for
larger decisions but we make decisions
as i kind of alluded to earlier on on an
individual
feature function basis i think one one
thing that
a spreadsheet's really good for is that
you are creating this
very dynamic list where you can wait
and and measure these different options
accordingly
but i think that it's also not just a
checklist
where it's down a single side of yes or
no does this function or feature exist
there's a lot of different variables on
well how well does it do that or
not just the priority but the importance
in terms of
are those features exactly related to
the business or
you know are we going to have to adjust
and
come up with hidden costs for each one
of those features
so what i mean by that is is there are
some other techniques
we use a technique when actually mapping
out what software needs to do
called user story mapping and we do a
slicing
technique and it's it really comes from
product management
of you know you've probably heard of
like must have or nice to haves
in terms of priority but this is in
terms of every single story
underneath a feature and i think
breaking it down
into that specific level where you're
not just evaluating
features and does this have the ability
to create accounts
it's okay how specific can we get into
accounts
and every single action we really like
the technique of user story mapping
to get into all of those details and at
the end of the day that's a ton of work
and a ton of stuff to manage
especially when you're dealing with well
a question of should we build our own
crm or should we adopt salesforce or
a huge platform like that it may be too
much
but for most of the decisions that we
work through we love that technique
and do you have to do that for every
single kind of vendor because i would
imagine like you just mentioned
salesforce and the first thing i thought
of was
do you need a framework like this for
slack for stripe because for some of
these they almost seem like no-brainers
but there's definitely other ones where
it's it's much fuzzier territory so do
you have prescriptions for certain sort
of no-brainers versus ones that require
more effort
we recreate a lot of stuff over and over
again
in just the the type of work that we do
when we build products from scratch
i think the the one that came to mind
was was stripe
that is something that we just returned
to that
just the cost in general of choosing a
different vendor
braintree or something like that or
there's tons of payment systems out
there now
that handle a lot more
than just the api approach so charge b
and
billing into a subscription sas model
how much control and how much refinement
do we need over that so
we have that playbook and we don't
return to that in most cases
but at the same time when we have the
opportunity we are out there evaluating
new cases and seeing
what those trade-offs are and so we're
making that investment for our clients
so that we don't have to make it
on every single new build this is
actually a really good point that it's
not just build versus buy it's also buy
versus buy
you could very much know okay we're
totally not going to roll our own
payment software but we don't know if
we're going to use stripe or
braintree so do you have specific kinds
of checklists or modifications if you
know it's not built versus buy but it's
like
deciding between different vendors yeah
absolutely vendor size is huge and so
this is where
it actually gets a lot more complex is
that before
most of these you know you have your
major players in the market and
if it doesn't matter if it's not too
crucial like you're just starting out in
the marketplace and you're just trying
to prove product market fit
so we don't even need to really care
about are we choosing the best
credit card rates that are out there and
are we negotiating with all these
different vendors because our volume is
really low
yeah throw in strike you know call it a
day move on
if we need to get into some of the the
very specific details of
you know there's a large cost benefit
analysis
between these vendors so we're uh we're
a bandwidth
partner and bandwidth does communication
pipelines so cpas is
essentially a twilio competitor that
allows you to do messaging and
voice apis directly to telecom providers
and one of their major advantages is
that they're
a lot more cost effective than twilio
because they are a telecom provider
themselves
so those benefits and where we see a lot
of people
choose bandwidth is after they've used
twilio for a while
and they need to take advantage of those
those cost benefits because they're
seeing such massive scale
but starting out with bandwidth while
you're just testing a business model
you might not need that scale and so you
might be able to take advantage of
twilio's self-service onboarding as
opposed to bandwidth that
you need to talk to a salesperson so
it's not just a one and done it's
all throughout the life cycle whenever
you integrate with these partners
you need to make those decisions so
other things to consider in there
are definitely around what's the size of
the company
who are they owned by can you choose aws
if you're competing with amazon can you
choose to use github if you're competing
with microsoft now because they just got
acquired
there's tons of of options and things to
evaluate and things to consider for sure
how much does brand factor into your
calculus because you've mentioned that
sort of made me think like
how do you convince a company to go with
what was it cpas
instead of twilio right because even if
it doesn't
completely fit your solution oftentimes
brand is like a big thing that really
draws people like
i just i remember from many years ago
one of my previous companies
i remember trying to convince people to
use mithril js which is this
really small sort of mvc framework that
kind of competes with react
but i mean it's it's a super small brand
it doesn't have a lot of
big backing like react does or something
like that and so
you know brand is a big factor because
what comes with brand is support
and maintenance and enterprise offerings
so you know how do you factor that in
when you're trying to convince someone
like okay this might actually be the
right solution for your size company
even though there's a bigger sort of
stalwart out there that is
you know arguably has a better brand and
better support
i mean i think you hit the nail on the
head in terms of what that brand
actually means at the end of the day
the thing we hate as developers the most
is when someone comes in and says
well i just i just read this and i think
the thing we come up with
is a an airline magazine before kovit it
was always executives traveling on
airlines and reading about it and saying
yeah let's do this and let's change our
entire
company technology architecture based on
what i read in sky magazine or whatever
and what that means at the end of the
day is what's the supportability of it
long term how's it going to stay around
what are all these other factors that
come from it i think open source in
particular you brought up mithril is a
really
interesting point because we look at
things as detailed as how many stars on
github or how many issues or when was
the last commit
and how maintained is this open source
because open source is not just
buying it off the shelf because you have
the opportunity to
fork that repo and change it yourself
and if the licenses
allow you to contribute back into that
community and be a
a steward of that so it's closer to
an acquisition of software than just
buying software off the shelf because
you can get into the internals and you
have a lot more control over that
software
so as opposed to you're using a closed
framework from apple or microsoft
traditionally you're not able to really
get into those internals and you just
have to
wait for them to patch it whenever you
have a bug
so that whole partnership conversation
changes
so there's tons of details but i would
say that
one of the biggest things is just
long-term supportability how
are we going to be able to train people
and find other people in the marketplace
that
know these technologies and can ramp up
on them quickly
or is that a cost that we're going to
have to pay that hey if we invented our
own framework and
to compete with react our that internal
framework are we going to have to train
new developers on it
so there's tons of details in there i
will eat my words
if i ever find a developer who reads sky
magazine and finds out about some new
javascript framework
that would be hilarious but hey but it
did remind me did it really happen to
you one time
is that what you thought of that that
was more of an executive that wasn't a
developer and
he was like oh you know braintree's
doing this awesome stuff let's use them
over
over stripe and it's like well really
like
okay we can ramp up on a new technology
but this is what it'll mean long term
and
yeah there's all sorts of stuff that's
so funny well it did actually remind me
of
one piece which is you know you
mentioned that in open source software
you have some agency
to modify or fork the software but you
also kind of do with vendors too and one
of the things i was going to cover in
vendor management
is this idea of custom integration so
before we get to that part let's let's
start talking about sort of the the
buying solutions because i think with
with open source software it's a lot
easier because you don't have to pay any
money but
for these bigger vendors especially like
salesforce where you could be writing
really big
checks there's a really strenuous
process to go through when you start
thinking about these bigger vendors so
you know just from very beginning how do
you approach a vendor
with an intent to buy especially if
you're you're looking at multiple
vendors
yeah i think as a customer getting into
the right channel and positioning
yourself
in the right way that's that's really
attractive
to the vendor as a technical team
technical enabled organization like if
you're just a
buyer of off-the-shelf software versus
you're looking to integrate a solution
getting your technical team involved as
quickly as possible so
having them evaluate from a user
standpoint
what those apis look like what the
details of those apis look like what's
their support contracts
and getting into the nitty gritties is
often
overlooked so we were working on a
marketing project and an ad project
recently in the ad tech space
and integrating with a trade desk was
really interesting
because they're leading the market in so
many ways but
they also have their own proprietary api
that looks good on the surface but has a
lot of problems still because
they are innovating so quickly and so
really understanding what that support
contract looked like
i think was incredibly important from a
vendor management and
relationship perspective so you
mentioned the technical folks you want
to bring in the conversation
tell me tell me what that first convo
looks like if you're sending out the
zoom invite
and you want to invite people onto that
conversation with somebody else from the
other company
who are you bringing in are you bringing
in all the engineers the lead engineer
product manager who should come to that
conversation prepared
so i come at it from the the product
management perspective they're the ones
usually leading that conversation
sometimes it's led by technical of
here's a technical task that
or goal that product management has
created and and that the technical team
needs to fulfill in terms of feasibility
and so they're doing some research there
typically a lead engineer has enough
context to understand
the support all the development
requirements
product management is great and then
just the business side of it
so if product managers can can handle
the usability side technical people can
handle the
feasibility side then the business
managers need to focus on like the
viability side and ask those questions
and
really that triforce coming together
should cover
99 of the work that needs to be
understood and
really hammer that out and then in terms
of due diligence
how do you incorporate like what we
talked earlier about like a spreadsheet
or a checklist
we know what you want to cover in
general but are there any particular
items you really want to hammer on on
that first conversation
on the very first one i'm i'm not so
sure
of if there's any like quick wins to get
you to a yes or no
maybe sticking points so after the
second time you've done this if you've
done a deeper dive on one vendor and you
know you really want to
check that against somebody else so for
example a big difference between
bandwidth and twilio
is voicemail detection on outbound calls
right now that's a limitation of the
bandwidth api it doesn't have that
functionality
and so we know right away when
evaluating
vendors that that's one thing that's
different between those and
just through past investigation we know
that's a sticking point
and then knowing yourself and your own
organization i think is really important
of
if you have any differences or ways of
operating that
you know that most other buyers of
software don't have
that's a really good way of saying just
hey real quick up front
we know we sign contracts that look like
this and we can't sign contracts that
look like that so before we waste each
other's time
let's just put that on the table well
that does bring me to a good point
back to my previous point about the
custom integrations and sort of forking
software is
one lever you can really pull is that if
people want your business
just because they can't do it now
doesn't mean they can't do it in the
future so
you know is it worthwhile to start
talking right away about custom
integrations or what the company can
offer because
just because it's not on the features
home page doesn't necessarily mean it
can't be done in general
yeah and a lot of companies especially
the smaller ones are willing to
do a whole lot to gain that business so
looking at the size of their
organization and what they're planning
on
so totally another example we work with
a small company startup out of yc
called courier and essentially
you have all these email providers like
sendgrid and
and mailchimp that can just
transactionally send emails
but they live on top of all those
systems and allow you to send
notifications just data to courier and
then they disperse it over whatever
channel you want to use it so email text
anything else and they as a as a company
are really small
just out of y combinator and they're
willing to like
say hey you want to integrate with 20
other people yeah
we'll build them for you we'll willing
to do that so understanding
what those company sizes are and what
their goals
as a company are so like they're talking
about raising funding and
when you raise funds you care about
traction and so you're willing to do a
whole lot
for that traction purpose and making it
a mutually beneficial
relationship like can this become a case
study can this
feature be used for 10 of their other
clients and
really putting yourself in the vendor
shoes of what they're looking for
like that's going to be a totally
different conversation than going to
microsoft and talking to
just an account exec and basically being
like
does office support this yes or no like
depends on
what you can really offer and what you
can bring to them but in general do you
think it's a good idea to say
anything's possible i should at least
come you know prepared with the idea
that hey
things are negotiable it's not as black
and white as whatever is listed
yeah for the majority of companies
absolutely totally depends on the size
of who you are and what you're bringing
we operate and a lot more of the startup
space so
understanding startup vendors and and
what their
goals are are very different and
absolutely have that mindset
but again if if that's all that we are
and we reach out to twilio and say hey
you don't have this feature or this
function
what's the likelihood of that is that
gonna is that even on your roadmap
and a lot of companies are starting to
to bring their roadmaps more public and
have that information be transparent
with their current customers
but that sales conversation is still
very different
and so as it evolves as that sales
conversation evolved i know you
mentioned that
in the first conversation it doesn't
necessarily mean there are certain
questions you have to ask then but
throughout the timeline of your
conversations with a vendor
what questions do you absolutely have to
ask like the things i'm thinking of are
great limiting of the apis if the apis
are tiered legal considerations i think
you sort of touched on that
uh public versus private documentation
you know what things are you trying to
ask them to get clear answers on at some
point in the conversation
yeah absolutely sharing your
requirements and your business
perspective
should translate into their organization
and their sales team
so you mentioned rate limiting i'm just
sharing
here's here's our project requirements
from a technical perspective like
this is how many messages we need to
send over over this much time
this is the strategy of how we were
thinking of implementing
your api does that make sense does that
align to
your requirements are there anything
that we should look out for
there asking them for
that system design a good salesperson
will
meet you where you are a bad one will
make you translate that
into their terms so understanding those
differences and what you're looking for
in that relationship
you mentioned just new features
understanding like
what is their professional service
offering and if they're going to
send you to a pro-serve team like that
to onboard into their system
or are they going to you know
onboard you and support you as part of
that contract for free
i think those questions really depend on
a lot of the
the type of software that you're looking
for
but around support contract lengths and
other legal considerations there matter
so
the other thing on legal considerations
that that comes to mind is
for compliance purposes how they treat
your data
is becoming so much more important these
days with gdpr
and ccpa changes that
what your legal team needs to be able to
support and
share publicly about what you do with
customer data
is definitely part of the sales process
for most
sas platforms do you have any tips for
talking about
the sort of secret sauce because you
know one of the things i struggled with
is if you tell them really everything
about your business
for the vendor in particular you might
get
a clear answer on something but there's
definitely this hesitation of
well you know they are another company
and do i really want to reveal
certain secrets it's it's kind of
difficult it's really hard you know if
you say everything in a sense
it could be very helpful in helping you
find the right solution but on the other
hand you don't want to do anything that
would be
you know compromising for the moat of
your business so what's a good way
to navigate revealing information when
trying to get to the correct solution
we're very opinionated on this we take a
lean startup approach which has the
mindset of be transparent about
everything share everything
an idea is worthless but
the execution is everything and from
that perspective
we tend to over share i don't think it's
ever
come back to hurt us in our eight years
it has only helped us
the standpoint that i could see where it
would really hurt
is if you're talking to somebody that
could be a competitor
at that point we rely on the legal
system
of patents and protection from
competition when sharing something
that's just
very early stage in development but the
majority of the time
what we're talking to other people about
is far enough away from our secret sauce
of our business
and is more generally understood there's
probably some other
kind of smoking mirrors that you could
do of you know if you're in the
healthcare space but
you really want to have some kind of
messaging system and you need to reach
out to twilio and get this set up
in a vendor relationship then
you could say hey i'm in this other
similar enough
industry and not reveal all the details
but we haven't had to play any of those
games
even on behalf of our clients that's
that's been our experience there
have you ever had any red flags where
you just you know regardless of the kind
of solution where you just
heard something from a vendor or there
was something that the revender revealed
where you said okay hit the eject button
i'm out
anything that you look for that other
folks should know about when dealing
with
reliable vendors yeah business practices
how easy it is to get on a development
team or how
sales talks to a development team as
soon as you start seeing those inner
workings of their company
i think is incredibly important anytime
a sales person
like gives you an effort estimate when
you're talking about professional
services or something like that and
there's just a lot that you can glean
just thinking about it in terms of well
if i was in that role i wouldn't want my
sales team promising that or doing that
thing that
we haven't had the opportunity to even
like talk about or think about so
there's tons of like are they doing the
same business practices and operating
the same way that
our organization operates or you know
are they just trying to
nickel and dime their vendors or
something like that those are those are
big red flags for us
that f1 is really interesting so are you
saying that giving an effort estimate is
a problem it's that the sales person's
doing it
on the fly on behalf of a development
team that is concerning
yeah yeah i would definitely say that
it's like who's giving the estimate
have they talked about it before we hear
a lot like oh that's really easy we
could just do it this way
and it's like well is that really easy
have you guys thought through this
problem or are you just trying to
marginalize
the problem itself and don't really
quite understand it yet
and so having that experience of going
through these integrations and building
them and
you know what those support teams and
contracts look like
there's definitely being around the
block and doing it so many times you
you pick up on those people's interests
and incentives to
say what you want to hear versus give
you a realistic
response to that got it so how does that
factor into demos like
who can you ask to show a demo and when
is
asking for a demo the right time in the
sales conversation
in a demo looking at are they showing
you spreadsheets and screenshots are
they showing you current state or
are they showing you future state is
really important to suss out
you can definitely ask for a demo as
soon as possible that's what most sales
processes are these days are either
self-service online
or schedule a demo getting behind and
into the details of the demo
asking for a free account is something
that we do
very often of well we just want to try
this out get the tires ourselves
you know not have a sales person there
with us so just like buying a car
hey can i give you my license and sign a
paperwork or something like that to some
degree
that lets me take it out for a test
drive all that's really common these
days in
sas offerings because it costs them
next to nothing to do and it's only
upside
for them so tons of techniques like that
that you can use
got it so you know i think for certain
ones like slack it's really easy to get
started because you just
download the software it's free and you
just start playing around with it i'm
actually very curious about in terms of
buy evaluation like let's say it's a
bigger
piece of software like salesforce where
there's an api and there are
integrations
and there's a lot of leg work that needs
to be done just to get it set up and
running
how do you go about evaluating vendor
software because i can tell you from the
example i had before
we had like 80 something items that we
had to enumerate through
and it was a real slog to go okay what
api connects to this particular feature
you know is there a way that you
streamline that process you know for the
developers listening
and they know they have to evaluate an
api and that api could be massive
how do you actually begin to start
looking through this stuff and
evaluating it appropriately
yeah and in terms of quick wins or
silver bullets i don't know if there
is many one of the techniques that we've
done
that may kind of fall under that
category is
we go and ask outside help hey if you
were to do this for me as a professional
service
how much would it cost you to do it like
you have experts on your team that have
implemented salesforce before
how much would you charge me to
implement salesforce and so
if you then extrapolate those numbers
and say hey they're looking for 20 to 30
margins and they have experts that have
done this before
you know i could roughly think that y is
now my cost for doing this and so from a
high level business evaluation
that might tell you from a like getting
into every single story and every single
detail you know that is designing out
creating those requirements and building
that solution
that is a process of discovery that kind
of toes the line between
hey is this just evaluating the software
or is this actually
going and integrating it and part of
that integration so
doing it from the standpoint of well
here's what we need to integrate
let's kind of abstract that and say okay
well stripe
fits in here but braintree fits in this
other way
and how they process it let's design it
for our problem space and our solution
inside of our organization and then see
how that modularly can swap in and out
all these other vendors
and if it can't be swapped in and out
that might be a
code smell essentially of the design
that says
hey maybe our design isn't really well
thought out in this area and we need to
discover those requirements on our own
because no vendor is going to
necessarily do that for you it's really
the part
that your organization owns as part of
that integration or
buying of that software that salesforce
example is really interesting
so if i heard you correctly are you
saying that let's say salesforce says
yeah here's our software you want to
start evaluating it go ahead are you
saying that you could
sort of i guess like additional calculus
to this is you could hire
an external firm who's integrated
salesforce before and say hey what's the
cost of you evaluating it
for our integration is that kind of the
idea
i wouldn't say just evaluating it i
would say doing that full integration
like if you were to hire a separate team
to actually come in and do that
integration
maybe there is an evaluation stage of
that on how that works and
and what that is for example we built
our own website we made this decision
when
we wanted to buy versus build we're not
a website development company please
don't come to us and ask us to build
your next website that's not what we do
but we went out and built our own
website because
one of the things that we evaluated was
should we use hubspot in their marketing
platform to build our website
and we said okay well how much is this
going to cost us to build it we didn't
know so we reached out to a professional
services
hubspot company and they said it'll cost
us
45 grand to build what you're looking
for and i said okay we'll take out 20
margins that's how much it'll cost me to
build on top of
hubspot if i had a team of excellent
hubspot developers
and i didn't and so we said okay well
hubspot's probably not the platform for
us
like i don't want to pay a bmw to build
a website that's not
the level of investment that we're doing
right now so
understanding and using that short code
of
hey what are other organizations doing
what are they spending there
finding that experience share at the end
of the day allowed us to make that
decision
very quickly that's an interesting
hidden cost i didn't think about which
actually might be a savings if you pivot
it the right way which is okay
we know we're going to buy salesforce
versus building ourselves because
crm software is definitely very
standardized but then there's that sort
of
additional cost of okay well we could
integrate it ourselves
which could have some additional cost or
we could have someone else integrated
which is like yet another expense on top
but if the math works out that an
external vendor integrating is actually
cheaper than
trying to integrate it yourself you not
only get the benefit
of that purchase software which does the
commodity thing you don't need to do
but in addition you don't even need to
integrate it either because you've got
somebody else who's got more experience
and can probably do it
cheaper and faster than you could do it
internally yeah there is a double-edged
sword
to that so we are a bandwidth integrator
through our partnership there
we're an integrator of segment and
a couple of other systems that we just
have a lot of experience with
through our partnerships and the
other expense is just getting that
integrator up to speed on what your
requirements are and what your business
is
if they're truly experts and they've
done that dozens of times
then they should absolutely know that
and
have the right questions to ask and
accelerate that process but they should
also just have a rule of thumb of hey
this is how much it costs to do
that kind of integration and this is how
much it's cost us in the past
so relying on that expertise and someone
that's been there absolutely
well plus it's probably not just bottom
line too right like if you're hiring an
expert
maybe part of what you're paying for is
the convenience right it doesn't
necessarily mean the cheapest
is the best it could mean that okay well
we're actually gonna go with an external
vendor and it might cost us
slightly more but we know we're gonna
get a higher quality piece of software
and we know we have an expert who can do
it in a much faster timeline even if
you know the actual cost of maybe 10
more of what we could do ourselves
and they're typically willing to support
that as well so
it's not just an initial integration
it's okay now you're integrated
now you got changes coming through how
do we build a longer term support
contract like an extra warranty
on top of the actual manufacturer of the
software if you will
that's a good point so if you have made
it to this stage and you're like really
ready to commit to buying
you know what does a good proof of
concept look like how do you know when
you have to play around with it enough
to know okay i think i'm ready to use
this you know because one thing i have
with my
my lead developers is if you're going to
dive into some really big software
you're really concerned
of well what about the unknown unknowns
that i don't know about yet a lot of
that
only comes from actually just using the
software so how do you know when you've
evaluated enough of it
i think you bring up an interesting
point is are you putting the right
people in front of it so are you putting
the actual
users if you're buying an api have
actual developers looked at it or just
your development leads
so those are some of your your more
expensive
processes is actually creating and using
that proof of concept to some degree
and all of the point of a proof of
concept is saving money from actually
going down a route too far and making a
mistake so it's this
it's this tightrope balance of have you
narrowed down
10 vendors that were initially on your
list into the two
that you want your development team to
look at to help you make that final
decision
and from that standpoint
like they need to actually get into it
and get into it from a use case and be
held accountable from
hey you're on the hook and are making
this decision
and if you put that accountability
behind them in the right way
where they get to make that final
decision of braintree versus strike
they're going to be bought in and
they're going to do
their work and not just give it a
once-over on their marketing page
they're going to actually go through
those create that proof of concepts
maybe stub out some actual code and see
what that looks like and
you know see if the proof is there so
getting the right people
is what what we as leaders can
definitely do and rely on those people
and
and hold them accountable and and get
their buy-in
so it's always going to be a leap of
faith then right like you're never gonna
get
perfect answers before you actually sign
on the dotted line but there definitely
are
it sounds like there are certain things
you can definitely look for before you
know you actually sign a check
it's more of what's the risk level and
what's the confidence level
but yeah everything is trying to tell
the future to somewhat
and no developer is going to be perfect
at planning
out every single case and and finding
those unknowns unknowns is
like they're unknowns for a reason and
the business might not even have all the
requirements down
it's about reducing that risk and
reducing
the unknowns and how much investment
can you put in up front before you it's
too much before it's
just actually implementing it it would
have been cheaper just to build
something and fail at it three times
before you do anything so it's
it's this balancing line and this levels
of commitment
kind of thing is you know are you just
dipping your toe in or
did you just jump in head first so all
right so
now you know that you've done all the
due diligence you can you have to make a
decision
if you decide that you're going to build
instead of buy how do you close out the
conversation amicably
i feel like when you you have a lot of
intent especially the further along you
get in the sales funnel
there's a lot of expectations about how
things are going to proceed forward is
there a way that you can ensure
that you maintain a strong business
relationship especially for you know for
example
you leave to not work with this vendor
but maybe two years from now
might be the right time to work with
them it's not necessarily a
no it could be a sorry we'll try later
do you have any tips along those lines
so from a sales perspective all knows
that we see
are not nows and that's how we look at
everything is
no just me it's not now timing's not
right you know stars didn't align
that's fine any mature salesperson will
understand that
especially if you're in the same
industry the world's too small
you're going to run into these people
again in the future so being amicable is
is really important the thing that i
keep coming back to in
in the personal work that i do is just
treat
those people how you would want to be
treated give them as much information as
you can
if they ask for like okay well who did
you go with why did we lose don't think
of it as like
well they're trying to keep you on and
they're trying to keep debating and
getting you back in the door you've
already told them that
you've gone a different direction but
give them the feedback so that they can
improve and
like stay on their mailing list and be
open for
them to reach back out when there's a
better time
i think sharing what you can and being
honest and truthful is good
but also you know if
they just walk away and stop
communicating realize that you know
that's part of
that relationship as well and it's
business at the end of the day and
people can be professional there so i
think it's really about
putting yourself in the other person's
shoes and creating an
amicable relationship that may come back
one day
and if you start going through that
build process you know what kind of
signals are you looking for where you
realize
okay maybe we do need to reach back out
or you know our internal solution just
isn't cutting it the way we thought it
was going to i
made a commitment to start building the
software and we ran into some snags
or the feature set blew up and it was
more things than we anticipated once we
started building
certain features it ballooned into a
larger project
how do you know when you have to really
commit
and follow this through all the way or
you know when
are the opportunities to reconnect or
re-evaluate
if you if you really feel like maybe
this isn't a permanent decision
yeah i don't i don't think anything is
necessarily a permanent decision there's
there's
all these factors are constantly moving
i think
there's usually some kind of pressure
that says
you know there's outside forces to some
degree saying
hey it's time to re-evaluate and re-look
at it to me it's always an opportunity
it's always something that's under
constant evaluation
but it's normally some kind of pressure
that's high enough that's pushing all
the other pressures and all the other
decisions
out of the way and into priority i don't
think that there's a natural
cadence but we as an organization for
example
make it a goal like once a quarter and
once a year to
re-look at different things so we
revisit our playbook every single time
we
go through a single play in that
playbook so every single time we
implement stripe
we say hey is stripe the best option or
has anyone
like is there anything else on deck that
we should definitely check out before we
get back into implementing stripe the
next time
but whenever we on a quarterly basis or
on a yearly basis we say hey is our our
subscriptions up for renewal on this
contract
you know is there any other software is
there anything else that we need to
change about it
before we get back into it and customer
success teams are doing the same thing
on the opposite side of those
relationships so
they have account managers that look at
renewal times and
look at the value that you're getting
out of their products and definitely
aren't
on that similar cadence okay so on the
flip side then
if you now know that you definitely want
to buy
instead of build and you know that from
the very beginning how do you start
comparing vendors we definitely talked
about that there's
sometimes situations of buy versus buy
but
let's say it's down to two vendors that
are both very close
you know you want to choose one of them
but you're having trouble really kind of
getting into the nitty-gritty
decisions between those two and you've
eliminated a lot of other possibilities
so how do you start comparing these
vendors to find
the solution that works for you you're
at that stage where you've already
narrowed down 10 into two
and you're just trying to compare the
last two i mean you can
be honest and straightforward with both
of those and even say hey these are the
the two that i'm it's between you and
this other person
what are some of the differences that i
should look at and
they are often much more versed in those
particular details and
might help you with some of that primer
but you know most of the time
i think we're very opinionated as people
and we have a pretty clear understanding
that
the pros and cons between the two and
we're just waiting on
a deciding factor after we've laid out
all the
the facts so it's pretty rare that we
actually end up with
two that are very similar in that
there's
differences in company size and all
these other factors that
really go into a lot of our decisions so
i think
as we're part of larger teams and larger
projects
that's where that decision gets bubbled
up higher and higher from someone away
from
the details and so it's about presenting
the details in the right way to that
person that ultimately needs to make
that decision
okay so when you are talking about
negotiation we all know that
especially in sas software there is no
real
sticker price like there are prices of
course for
the commodity offerings that they that
they offer but if you're doing with
these more custom integrations it's
absolutely based on the size of your
company the size of the
instances of the servers you're running
all that kind of stuff so how do you
actually start thinking about
negotiating on price in terms of the
more tangible things like
terms duration rate limits that kind of
stuff yeah
i think that everything's up for grabs
and
and negotiating from the same place with
your
salesperson the the person on the other
side of the the deal
making sure you guys understand the same
terms and understand the value of the
relationship and
and what's coming out there is
incredibly important
understanding their cycles and their
quotas that they go through
is incredibly advantageous to getting a
better price
so like there are times to buy when
they're trying to meet their quotas on
what kind of discounts that they've been
given access to give
and to handle and so building that
relationship
and and understanding that and also
being
time effective with their time
and just being like hey i really can't
do that is there anything else that you
can do
and just being like forthcoming and
understanding that
a salesperson's time is one of their
most valuable assets so
helping them be effective with that is
incredibly important so
just straight to the point but in in
terms of like
what are all those options and levers
that they can tweak we just ask a lot of
the times and say
well what other options can you tweak
here that's
very different for every single one of
those companies depending on what size
that they are
and how do you evaluate custom
integrations because that's the one
i feel like can balloon your cost the
most
and is also the most nebulous like if
you price out some software and you say
it's 59
a month that's a there's a clear reason
why they chose that price
based on some sas model right but when
they get into the
you know you always see this on the
pricing pages you've got like the the
basic tier model the enterprise model
and then they have
some sort of like custom model and they
never show the price they just go talk
to us which is usually language four hey
by the way this is super expensive
how do you even go about evaluating
whether the custom integration piece
is a good value or is fair and
reasonable
yeah i think that's a lot of an internal
perspective
on our business what's the value of that
integration how fast does it get there
how fast does it compare to all these
other opportunities of going out and
getting another party to do it or
getting theirs or getting our own team i
think
one piece that's hidden there is okay if
they do this custom integration for us
are they able to go out and resell that
custom integration
what's the longer term value for them
are are they adding these as core
features to their product or
is it really a truly one-off for them
and they never want to see or touch this
again
kind of thing so there's
definitely at least three other options
are can you get an outside vendor
that's a complete third party to do this
are they doing it
or are we doing the custom integration
or is it a hybrid
model and understanding those options
and
and those values and at least those
costs is definitely important
so translating it to full-time employee
equivalence
is one of those factors that you can
evaluate that price to see if it's
realistic or not
now we're sort of rounding the corner
here to the very end and we've made it
all the way through all these decisions
we know we're gonna buy
and we bought and now we started doing
the work how do you keep track of
progress
and evaluate slas to make sure that the
expectations you had from this vendor
are matched
because it's one thing to go okay cool
we know this software's gonna work for
us we want
to buy we bought we started integrating
there's obviously snags along the road
too because their interest
isn't getting your business but not
necessarily in
following through i mean you know
sometimes just custom integrations can
take longer than expected or
their support team is not as prompt as
you would expect them to be
so how do you keep the vendors honest
and how do you make sure that
you re-evaluate appropriately to make
sure that on the flip side of i built
and now i sort of have
second thoughts what about if you buy
how do you know when you have to accept
a certain level of
unknown there i guess the approach that
we've taken
is especially on custom integrations
it's our
duty as the end user is the end buyer of
that
to manage that as a project so just like
we would internally
stay on top of those people they might
have their own project manager
but we can't just let them go and
not pay attention to those details so we
need to do our diligence
on all of that along that side
so having our project manager that owns
it an internal champion a product owner
if you will
if it's more of an agile process that's
going to take a long time
and then that person is responsible for
your organization
of communicating out what's the status
and all managing all the stakeholders on
the buyer's side
that person is responsible for your
organization
of communicating out what's the status
and all managing all the stakeholders on
the buyer's side
because you really need that clear
communication that clear priority
as the bridge between the two
organizations you do not want
10 people giving that project manager
different requirements
and not having clear expectations so
from that perspective that's just
project management
101 on how we handle and how we
evaluate that if it comes down to like
hey this is really not working out and
they're breaking slas and
deciding when to to drop them i mean
there's
unfortunately this whole problem is is
much more common in the industry than it
should be
but there are you know some cost
fallacies that you got to watch out for
and keeping an eye on hey we've already
put this much money into it should we
really chase that money with more money
and is that truly going to solve the
problem or is that
the underlying problem who's responsible
for that
and who needs to fix that and do we need
to adjust contracts and
and come back to it so you know if
they're constantly breaking an sla
you know is more money going to fix that
are they doing that because they're
trying to cut corners because
you negotiated the price too low and
you're no longer an important
partner for them you know where is that
misalignment coming into play
and and how do you move there is a
renegotiation
got it well dan this has been super
helpful actually for you know for me
just not just as a host but as someone
who deals with build versus buy a lot
in my day-to-day work this has been a
really awesome conversation i really
appreciate you taking the time today to
speak with us on software engineering
radio
any final words or advice for people who
are
getting started in this world of build
versus buy for their software vendors
yeah i would say the biggest thing is
evaluate buy more often especially as
software developers our natural tendency
is just to build right away and
at the end of the day is that the right
business decision to make or not
so push against our natural tendencies
and and shoot for more and
you know if you need help as part of
this journey and need help evaluating
software we
we do it a lot do it a lot more than
actually
understood we do it just by the nature
of what it is so
feel free to reach out you can find us
at vaporware.net and
reach out to me personally i'm just dan
at vaporware awesome well again
thank you very much dan moore for coming
on software engineering radio
thanks adam thanks for listening to sc
radio an educational program brought to
you by ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se-radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening